We start today, today's דף *daf* is ל"ו *Lamed Vav*, thirty-six.
And we pick up on the bottom of ל"ה עמוד Amode, ב׳
*Lamed Hey Amud Bet*.
And let's see.
We're up to, yes, so we had had a fascinating range of
debate about who can you trust when it comes to the fact
that this מום mum, דבכור *mum d'bechor* was made naturally and was
not made by the owner and either from positions that either basically
said that it was contextual about who stands to benefit and that
you cannot gain from this certainly from the person themselves, the owners
who are benefiting, or רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that basically doesn't believe
the class of כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* regardless of whether they are personally
benefiting in this situation. And now let's take a look about how
we rule. About a range of opinions about how we rule. And
so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this, איתמר *itmar*, it is
about ten lines from the bottom. איתמר *itmar* is the first word
on the line, maybe about twelve lines from the bottom. רב נחמן
אמר הלכה halacha כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל *Rav Nachman amar halacha k’Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel*, we rule like רבי שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel*. רבי שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel* says somebody
is believed about somebody else. You're just not believed about your own,
the blemishes on your own בכור bechor *bechor*, but you're believed about
somebody else's. Presumably even a relative. רבא Rava אמר הלכה כרבי יוסי
*Rava amar halacha k’Rabbi Yosi*. רבא *Rava* says we rule like רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*, which is a variation of רבי שמעון בן גמליאל
*Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel*, except what רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* says is
that family members are not believed on other family members. So you
would be believed on other people but not on your own family
members in terms of how this blemish came about. And so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ובעיא רבא הכי *uvia Rava hachi*, did
רבא *Rava* really say this? והאמר רבא *v’amar Rava*, בעלים עומדים עמנו
בבכור *ba’alim omdim imanu babachor*? If witnesses testify that the owners were
standing with us outside of their house. נכנס שלם ויצא חבול *nichnas
shalem v’yatza chavul*, and the sheep went into the house perfect and
it came out injured. ויעידן עליו *v’yeidan alav*, then they could testify.
Who can testify? Presumably the other family members that are in the
house. So you see you can trust family members as long as
they're not the technical owner about that it happened by itself. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אימה כל בעלים עומדים *eima kol ba’alim
omdim*. Okay, so what it means is that all the owners were
outside. So if all the owners are outside, so of course, what
else happened? So רש״י *Rashi* says well maybe a shepherd is inside
the house. Okay, the shepherd, I don't know, took them into the
house, who knows, but all the owners are outside and the shepherd
is saying that this מום mum, *mum*, this blemish came accidentally. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says,
ולא חיישינן *v’lo chaishinan*, and we're not concerned that somebody is lying,
the shepherd is lying. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, אי הכי
מאי למימרא *ee hachi mai l’meimra*? So that's obvious then, if none
of the owners are testifying, none of the family members, what's the
חידוש chidush *chiddush*? No, מהו דתימא ניחוש לחשדא *mahu d’teima nichosh l’chashada*,
we maybe should still be concerned about lying and deception. Maybe the
shepherd, you know, might be,
they might slip him a five or something if he testifies to
this, so maybe you're concerned about that. קא משמע לן ka mashmalan
*kamashma lan* that we're not. As long as it's all the family
members on the outside. Or רש״י *Rashi* says maybe the owners laid
a trap for him inside. Maybe they put like a lot of
like barbed wire right by the front door or something. Anyway we're
not concerned. So anyway now you have a position, one is that
we believe you about, or is about somebody else. The other is
only about non-family members. Now the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* wraps this up,
והלכתא V'hilchasa, כרבי שמעון בן גמליאל *v’hilchata k’Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel*, we
rule like רבי שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel*, you're believed
about somebody else even family members. ודווקא בנו ובתו *v’davka bno u’vito*,
only somebody like your son or daughter are believed about the father,
or the father about the children let's say. אבל אשתו לא *aval
ishto lo*, a man's wife is not believed about for him. מאי
טעמא *mai ta’ama*, what's the reason? Wait a minute Bobby before you
get upset, אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo דמי *ishto k’gufo dami*. Your wife
is like yourself, which means if you want an analog in secular
law, a spouse cannot be compelled to testify against another spouse, right?
So here, which is exactly, that's a little bit different, I think
that's in order to allow for, you know, for sharing of confidences
within marriage and without having to be concerned that they'll be used
against you. But here the sense is that, you know, the, now
look, it is true it says it from the male perspective, okay,
but I would think that maybe we could sort of generalize it
and basically say that, you know, when it comes to your spouse,
you know, people are willing to do things for their spouses, even
if it sometimes means a little of compromising of their integrity. That's
often the reality of the relationship, that sometimes you will do something.
I do not take this at all to be a statement about
women per se. I take this to be about a statement about
the nature of marriage and how come sometimes we will stretch ourselves
even for things that we maybe shouldn't be doing. What?
Would you believe a husband?
Well that would be the question. Let's say the wife would be
the owner of the sheep, would you believe the husband? So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* doesn't address that, but I don't think, I
do not think that we're making a distinction about that. I really
think we're talking about the nature of the marital relationship. I don't,
I have not seen if there's literature on that question. Okay, so
that is that issue. Now I do want to say, and this
is something we're going to get to, that we should note that
this is different from normal areas of כשרות *kashrut*. Normal areas of
כשרות *kashrut* you're believed for something that affects you. even if I'm,
you know, like for like I can testify, yeah, I bought all
this meat in a כשר *kosher* store, you know, it's all כשר
*kosher*,
I believe my spouse, my spouse believes me, guests believe us, you
know, you're believed in all those areas and we're not saying, oh,
you've got a vested interest, we can't trust anybody about their כשרות
*kashrus* unless somebody else testifies about it. Now, there could be technical
reasons for that, like one reason is because with a lot of
the כשרות *kashrus* issues, we say it's בידו *beyado*. You have the
ability to control the situation, you could have always gone to the
כשר *kosher* store, not the non-כשר *kosher*, that gives you extra believability.
Here, no, it's slightly different. But anyway, but here, here it's not
בידו *beyado*. If you have an animal that's a בכור bechor *bechor*,
it's not within your ability to make it a מום mum *mum*.
So that, no, not הלכתית *halachically* within your ability to make a
מום mum *mum*. So therefore, that might be part of the issue.
But the other part of the issue certainly seems to be that
this really seems to be a general exception to the rules of
believing somebody in איסור והיתר issur v'heter *issur v'heter* and כשרות *kashrus*
because as we see the entire class of כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* were
suspect, right? So there seems to have clearly been, it's a case
with like such a major obstacle. Here you have this animal you
can do absolutely nothing with, and you have to keep on raising
it and feeding it or whatever until it gets a מום mum
*mum*. So which leads to the fact that the entire class of
כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* is suspect. That could lead to the fact
that even if you're not רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*, the current owner
is suspect. So you know, it's a special case where people are,
you know, people rationalize and people find, people do go ahead and
do the thing. So it's a special area I think where there
was particular suspicion and therefore we had to say, okay, so who
are you going to believe, who are you not going to believe,
we'll believe anybody other than the immediate owners, even the, but in
the end we take the most lenient position, you know, other than
the spouse issue, we basically, the only person we don't believe is
the immediate owner, even family members are believed. But the point I'm
making is that even though there's a range of positions here and
we take the most lenient, even this is more strict than normal
כשרות *kashrus* areas. Normal כשרות *kashrus* areas, you know, or איסור והיתר
issur v'heter *issur v'heter* areas, you know, we believe people even if
they're the owners, even if they have a vested interest and so
on. So it seems to be that this was really a special
case that there were special concerns. But there's also the technical aspect
that I said, that it's not בידו *beyado*, there's no way to
הלכתית *halachically* achieve your end result. Yes.
Yeah, that's what I was trying to understand because exactly that point.
So you're saying is that this is more of an exception, it
can't really necessarily apply a general principle.
We don't apply it in other places.
No, meaning because of whatever it is, you know, like you don't
abstract.
Well, you could ask questions about other, right, that's correct. You could
ask questions about other cases where it's not בידו *beyado*, but as
a general rule this is seen as very, very בכור bechor. *bechor*
local because of specific, because there was a reality that people were
not so, that there was a very strong יצר הרע *yetzer hara*
by בכור bechor. *bechor* and people did cheat, which is why we
have all of these statements about how
to, I understand this בידו *beyado* thing, it's also בידו *beyado* to
not eat כשר *kosher* either.
No, no, but to make the meat in front of you כשר
*kosher*, you could have bought, you know, you could have gone to
the store and bought כשר *kosher* meat. Or to say that it
was שחט *shechted* properly, you could have ensured that you שחט *shechted*
it properly.
Here, if you start with a חפצא *cheftza* of value, you could
sell it to a non-Jew.
Right,
there's, it's not an ongoing thing.
Right, so that's the argument that the יצר הרע *yetzer hara* isn't
as great, correct, correct, exactly.
Rabbi, can you just repeat which category of בכור bechors. *bechor* this
is?
This is a בכור bechor. *bechor* with nowadays in the hands of
a כהן kohen *kohen* that you gave it to a כהן kohen
*kohen*, it's a בכור bechor. *bechor* of a sheep or a goat
or a cow that you can't do, it has the קדושה *kedusha*
of a קרבן korban *korban* and you can't do anything with it
until it gets a מום mum *mum*. Once it gets a מום
mum *mum*, because there's no
בית המקדש beit hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. Exactly, exactly. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר ליה Amar lei, רב פפא
לאביי *Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye*, רבי מאיר דאמר החשוד על הדבר
לא דנו ולא מעידו *Rebbi Meir d'amar hachashud al hadavar lo dano
v'lo meido*,
this is the question that some of you were asking yesterday, let's
make a little reductio ad absurdum. According to רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
that says if you're suspect about something you can never testify about
it or sit on a בית דין *Beis Din* about it, and
כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* as a class are suspect about בכור bechor. *bechor*,
and you can't even trust them about another כהן kohen *kohen* and
a total stranger, they just completely are compromised in that area. So
according to that, וקאמר רבי מאיר *v'ka'amar Rebbi Meir*, and we know
another רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says, if you remember from a few
דפים *dafim* ago, החשוד לדבר אחד חשוד chashud לכל התורה כולה *hachashud
l'davar echad chashud l'chol haTorah kullah*, that once you're suspect for one
thing you can't be trusted about anything, so you combine the two
statements and כהנים Kohanim הכי נמי דלא דייני דינא *kohanim hachi nami
d'lo dayni dina*? Do you mean a כהן Kohen *kohen* can never
sit on a בית דין *Beis Din*? You can never trust a
כהן Kohen *kohen* for anything? Right, because if they're suspect for one
they're suspect for everything. והכתיב *V'haksiv*, the פסוק *pasuk* says, ועל פיהם
יהיה כל ריב וכל נגע *v'al pihem yihyeh kol riv v'chol naga*,
that they're the ones that you know determine all halachic issues. So
it's true that sort of transferred to you know to the sages,
but nevertheless do you really mean to say that כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*
now have to be completely rejected to testify about anything, to sit
on any בית דין *Beis Din*? כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*? That's, so even
though we had no problem saying that they were suspect about בכור
bechor *bechor*, we're not prepared to basically completely disqualify them from any
type of a religious role. Yes.
Isn't that saying that our, we're equating כהנים kohanim *kohanim* with the
judges, we're really saying
all, we're saying... Which is a monetary, which is a monetary
right, a
suspect is, no no
no, חשוד על הבכור
*chashud al ha-bechor* means he is suspect.
That's because of the particular reality. He is dishonest.
Yeah, but it's not that, no
no, but it's not that
we're saying now a general statement as I was saying before. That
would have made our lives impossible. A general statement that anytime anybody
stands to benefit, has an interest in something, we assume they're lying
about it. We normally don't say that, right? We normally say, I
mean, maybe if it was a straight issue about a civil case
in דיני ממונות dinei mamonos, *dinei mammonos*, we suspect each side and
we don't believe anybody. But if it's a question about איסור והיתר
*issur v'heter*, like if a butcher, technically you do not need a
השגחה *hashgacha*. If a butcher comes and tells you "my meat is
כשר *kosher*" or you go into a restaurant and the guy says
"it's all כשר *kosher*", although they obviously have a very serious financial
interest
there, technically you're allowed to believe them. Certainly I can believe you
when I go to your house and you tell me you're serving
כשר *kosher* food, right? So we normally say עד אחד נאמן ne'eman,
באיסורין *ed echad ne'eman b'issurin*,
one witness is believed when it comes to sort of כשרות *kashrus*
and איסור והיתר *issur v'heter* regardless of personal gain. The בכור bechor,
*Bechor* was a particular area that we explored yesterday
that the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* have earned themselves a reputation particularly in
this area that they can't be trusted.
But it were also just said that על פיהם יהיה כל ריב
*al pihem yihiye kol riv*.
That's the question. How can you say that we generally suspect them
about the בכור bechor *Bechor* and we continue to trust them in
other areas? That's exactly the problem it's asking. Right. But it's not
saying that anybody who's a judge is automatically suspect. It's not the
reverse. It's saying given that you're suspect, how do we trust you
as a judge?
No, at that time they're assuming that the judges are כהנים kohanim
*Kohanim*.
Right, at least in the time of the תורה Torah. *Torah*. Right.
I mean the פסוק *pasuk* that they're quoting.
Right. So we are saying we have to suspect all our judges
for possibly being dishonest.
No, that's like one of your classic
logical fallacies. Just because Socrates is mortal doesn't mean that everybody who's
mortal is Socrates. Just because כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* are suspect on בכור
bechor. *Bechor* and they're judges doesn't mean that anybody who's a judge
is suspect on בכור bechor. *Bechor* or suspect on other things.
But it's saying all judges are כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* according to this.
At least they're saying, they're not living in biblical times, but at
least they're saying the תורה Torah. *Torah* places כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* as
judges. The way I understand this is even if nowadays they're not
the judge in class, that's more given over to the sages and
חז"ל *Chazal*, they certainly, we certainly acknowledge that they continue to function
in that role, not exclusively but they continue to function in that
role. Would you go so far to claim that כהנים *Kohanim* can
no longer function in that role, that we suspect them across the
board for everything? That's the question. It's not saying we suspect judges
for everything. If you're going to say we suspect כהנים *Kohanim* across
the board, are you going to exclude them from the role of
being judges? Can you really say that? That's all it's saying. Let's
read the answer. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אמר
דאמר רבי מאיר *emar de-amar Rebbi Meir*, we're at top of ל"ו
עמוד א' *lamed vav amud aleph*, when does רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
say that if you're suspect for one thing you're suspect across the
board? And when does רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* say that they're suspect
for בכור bechor, *Bechor*? לחששה *lechshasha*. That's just suspect. We don't have
any evidence. We're suspecting them as a class because we know that
it's a common thing. But we don't have any particular evidence about
any particular כהן kohen *Kohen* to suspect that. לאחזוקוני *l'achzukonei* is
to give them a חזקה *chazaka*, to meaning to establish the fact
and say we know that you in particular lie about these things.
מי אמר *mi amar*? He would not say that. Which basically means
the two statements of רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*, when does רבי מאיר
*Rebbi Meir* go so far to say once you're suspect for one
thing you're suspect across the board? That's when we know that you
in particular constantly do this. If I constantly see somebody sneaking into
a McDonald's and having a cheeseburger and I've seen them do it,
so I know that they are suspect for eating טרייף *treif*. I
know they eat טרייף *treif*. Meaning not just suspect, because they eat
טרייף *treif*, the חשוד *chashud* means I can never trust them when
they tell me about כשרות *kashrus* issues, but it's based on actual
fact and actual knowledge of regular habitual violation. Then I have to
suspect them about everything according to רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*. We don't
rule like רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*. We assume, and that was a
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* we had about a week ago, that people compartmentalize.
They rationalize why they're going to eat טרייף *treif* but why they're
going to be super פרום *frum* about שבת *Shabbos*. Or more troubling
and more common, they rationalize why they can cheat on their taxes
but why they're going to be super פרום *frum* about כשרות *kashrus*
and שבת *Shabbos*. Okay, so people compartmentalize. But according to רבי מאיר
*Rebbi Meir*, they don't. Once you allow yourself to violate one thing
you'll violate others. But that's when we have specific evidence about you
and we've seen regular violation. Here it's about a class of people
that we just suspect. We know that there are people amongst the
כהנים *Kohanim* that it's a common thing but it's not a specific
knowledge. Since that's true, we're not going to generalize and we're not
going to say that we don't trust כהנים *Kohanim* for anything. As
a class, the only thing we're going to say is we suspect
them when it comes to בכור bechor *Bechor*. Bobby.
Can you give a history of when this all happened
that?
No, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not clear when that happened. Presumably
it happened post בית המקדש beit hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* because then they
had no way of benefiting from it. Presumably at the time of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, then they could with a
שלעפ *schlep*, but they could bring it to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and eat
it in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. Okay, maybe it's also not even such a
שלעפ *schlep*, maybe you sell it to somebody who's going to bring
it to, well actually I don't know if you could do that
exactly. But whatever it is, anyway, but
but there it's only a שלעפ *schlep* factor. Here, after the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, there's no way you could benefit from
it, do anything with it until it got a מום mum *mum*.
So presumably it happened post בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Then they would
have to judge it. I understand, so it's not a technical question
of the פסוק *pasuk*. It's not, you know, what it, it's quoting
the פסוק *pasuk* for like emphasis, you know, the same כהנים *Kohanim*
who the תורה *Torah* says play this role, even though parenthetically nowadays
they don't really play that role, really that role is played more
by the sages, but nevertheless, they're given all this status in the
תורה *Torah*, do you really think we're going to exclude them from
ever being, you know, being judges and ever being, you know, playing
that type of authority? So because in a way what it's also
doing, it's holding a mirror up to this shocking fact that here
you take the כהנים *Kohanim* that are such this elevated category of
people and we're basically saying that they're across the board suspect to
regularly violate in a particular area. Okay, so you have to, once
you're saying that, which is pretty radical according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, it's only רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* who suspects them across the
board, it's saying we're going to have to make it very specific.
We're not going to allow that to seep into other things as
well.
So it wouldn't necessarily be let's say my question yesterday, חשודא *chashuda*
like נגעים *negaim* to appear even though they have a very strong
incentive to say like oh I don't have a צרעת *tzara'as* because
you know otherwise...
Oh you mean to be מעיד *me'id* about somebody else about their
נגע *nega*?
Right. No, no, meaning like another כהן kohen *Kohen*. In other words,
I'm testifying
about this כהן kohen *Kohen*. Yeah, no, no, right. It's he says
it's just the evidence has shown that as a class, you know,
and obviously whenever you make something a class and you generalize, you,
you know, you overstate the fact because there's obviously a lot of
honest individuals amongst that class, but he just says it happens often
enough that כהנים *Kohanim* lie about this and it's a particular area
where the כהנים *Kohanim* have rationalized about why they allowed themselves to
do it. Okay, so that's according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So
even with רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* we limit it, but we don't
even rule like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So let's keep on going.
איבעיא להו *Iba'u lehu*, they raised the question, עד מפי עד ed
mi-pi ed *ed mi-pi ed*, מהו לעדות בכור bechor. *mahu le-eidus bechor*?
How about second-hand testimony? Okay, which means that I come and I
say, Michael, I come and I say, oh, Michael told me that
he saw that that sheep got a blemish all by itself. Michael
isn't around, can we trust me, right? If the כהן kohen. *Kohen*
has it here, Dov here's the כהן kohen. *Kohen*, he's got it
in his house, he cannot be trusted how it got it, the
owner can't, forget רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, the owner can't be trusted
how he got it, we're not going to let him שחט *shacht*
it until he brings some evidence about how that happened. So let's
say Michael was the shepherd, he saw it, but he's not around,
but he told me. Okay, would I be believed to testify although
I'm not giving direct testimony about this? I have to tell you
by the way that once we don't believe the, well, okay, maybe
we only exclude the owners and the shepherd is the most common
person to see it, but the very fact that you need testimony
is going to make it so much more impossible, you realize, because
how often will it be that the animal will get a מום
mum. *mum* and nobody has any clue how it got the מום
mum? *mum*? Right? So how do you testify on the absence of
something? I see, you can't say I saw that no, I didn't
see anybody, that doesn't matter, maybe somebody did it and you're not
aware of it, right? So you actually have to have witnessed it
getting the מום *mum*. So just the very fact that you demand
testimony, even if you were to believe everybody, you know, it itself
makes it that much harder. But anyway, so now becomes the question,
at least we'll loosen it up a little bit, maybe we'll allow
second-hand testimony. So let's take a look. רב אסי *Rav Assi* אמר
*amar*, רב אמי *Rav Ammi* some say says, אסור *assur*, it's forbidden.
רב אשי *Rav Ashi* שרי *shari*, רב אשי *Rav Ashi* said it's
permissible. Here you have a little mnemonic, Assi assur and Ashi shari.
Okay, so anyway, so אמר ליה Amar lei רב אסי לרב אשי
*amar lei Rav Assi le-Rav Ashi*, so רב אסי *Rav Assi* said
to רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, והתניא דבי מנשה אין עד מפי עד
כשר אלא לעדות אשה *ve-ha tanya de-bei Menashe ein ed mi-pi ed
kasher ela le-eidus isha*, that you cannot trust second-hand testimony except when
it comes to testifying about a woman. What's the case? About a
woman's husband died and in a faraway land and we don't, or
there's testimony he died, we don't know for sure, you want this
woman to remain an עגונה *agunah* the rest of her life until
there's two witnesses or until she gets a גט get *get*? So
no, here חז"ל *Chazal* allowed second-hand testimony as sufficient basis to assume
the husband died to address the עגונה *agunah* situation and to let
the husband remarry. So he says we only allowed second-hand testimony in
that extreme case, we don't allow it just for something like בכור
bechor. *bechor*. So תני *tani*, so no, that's not how you should
read it. It doesn't mean testimony about a woman, it means אלא
לעדות שהאשה כשירה לה בלבד *ela le-eidus she-ha-isha keshera lah bilvad*, that
you allow second-hand testimony for the same types of things you allow
a woman to testify for. What types of things do you allow
a woman to testify for? So a classic example is כשרות *kashrus*
issues. עד אחד נאמן באיסורין *ed echad ne'eman be-issurin*. Right, רב משה
*Rav Moshe* actually has a תשובה *teshuvah* about whether a woman could
be a משגיח *mashgiach* in a, for כשרות *kashrus* and his question
was not whether you believe women, of course you do. I mean,
you know, as תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says in גיטין *Gittin*, you know,
every man who walks home and his wife puts dinner in front
of him, you're believing your wife about where the where the food
came from. The only question רב משה had was whether it was
considered to be like taking a position of authority or not. Okay,
anyway, but that's beside the point. Basically anything women are not believed
when it comes to formal testimony in court, which requires two witnesses.
Even there, I should say parenthetically, right, it's also why for example
women aren't witnesses, you know, at a קידושין kiddushin or at a
גט or so on. I should also say there parenthetically that in
the time of the ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz in particular, they found
a way, like workarounds to that, because there were many situations in
which women saw things and they needed, you know, their evidence. So
when it was a case of דיני ממונות, because cases of civil
cases allow for making decisions based on sort of circumstantial evidence rather
than on direct testimony, right, only corporal cases or formal things like
for עדות קידושין edus kiddushin need direct formal testimony. Other types of
things you can use evidence even if it's not testimony. So they
basically effectively accepted women's testimony in civil cases, particularly in areas that
there were no men around. Like it's actually interesting, one of the
earliest records of the idea of a woman's section had to do
with a debate about accepting a woman's testimony because, you know, nowadays
there's whole things about, hey, that's my seat and you took my
seat or whatever in שול. shul. Well, they had that way back
then too, and there's a whole question about who had the מזרח
mizrach seat in the women's section and only women knew. So you're
accepting sort of women's testimony about that. But in terms of formal
עדות, edus, right, that, you know, particularly when it comes to corporal
or civil cases or whatever according to the גמרא, Gemara I mean
according to the גמרא Gemara even civil, but anyway certainly when it
comes to sort of corporal cases and so on, that's only men.
But when it comes to other things, first of all for providing
evidence, women work, and particularly in the areas of איסור והיתר to
testify about the halachic status of things. So what he is saying
is that because women are believed in the status of בכור bechor
and the status of איסור והיתר and so on, therefore you can
also believe second-hand testimony. There are not formal requirements which would be
limited to men and to two men. Yes. You also believe one
witness, you don't need two.
Yes, go ahead. The principle we said before about אשתו כגופו ishto
k'gufo is very limited then. It's not across the board.
Right, a woman is believed on another man's בכור bechor, and a
person's daughter and mother is believed on his בכור. bechor The only
person that's not believed is the wife to the husband and maybe
the husband to the wife.
No, but we said אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo meaning a woman, we
accept her just like we accept the husband's testimony, we accept her.
No, that's not the principle about accepting a woman's testimony. אשתו כגופו
means that you assume that the interests of the wife and the
interests of the husband are the same.
Oh, I see. But so then it's a very limited application. It's
not wherever we believe him, we believe her. No, no, no, not
at all.
Right, I mean if you said that then what, then there'd be
no distinctions between men and women in הלכה as long as you're
married, then you have the status of a man. No, no, it
basically means the interests of the wife are the same as the
interests of the husband.
So he's saying that second-hand testimony is okay?
Is okay, according to him, that when it says only for testimony
of a woman, it doesn't mean relating to a woman, but a
woman's husband. It means since a woman is believed, it's not formal
testimony that needs two men, so therefore we accept second-hand testimony as
well. Okay. So רב יימר אמר עד מפי עד בבכור. Rav Yemar
amar ed mi-pi ed b'bechor. רב יימר Rav Yemar allowed second-hand testimony
by a בכור. bechor קרי עליה מרימר, Kari alei Maremar, all these
similar names, מרימר Maremar called him יימר שרי בוכרא, Yemar sharei buchra,
יימר Yemar the one who allows בכור. bechor. Okay, as רש"י Rashi
pointed out, if it wasn't obvious, that was a
put-down. Yeah. והלכתא, nevertheless, although we just had a put-down about that,
עד מפי עד כשר לעדות בכור. ed mi-pi ed kasher l'edus bechor.
We do allow second-hand testimony when it comes to the בכור. bechor,
Even after they say that? Just, yeah, that's our discussion now. Whether
we believe, what the general scope of עד מפי עד is not
being explored here. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, so רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar said, לא היו מוחזקין בו שהוא בכור. lo hayu muchzakin
bo she-hu bechor.
Let's say nobody knew the status of this sheep. Nobody knew it
was a בכור. bechor. ובא אחד, U-va echad, and a כהן kohen
came ואמר שהוא בכור. v'amar she-hu bechor. He says, hey, this animal
I have is a בכור. bechor, Just okay, who knew? ומומו עמו,
U-mumo imo, and here's the מום, and it has a blemish and
it happens by itself. So can you believe him that the blemish
happened by itself since nobody else knew it was a בכור bechor,
anyway? Now you say it's a course, we'll see what the גמרא
Gemara says. But by the way, this addresses the question I raised.
Part of the question I raised is that if you have, you
know, at most many, many things you'll have no testimony, nobody will
be a direct witness to. But the point is that if you
say that you don't need direct testimony if the thing, if nobody
else knew it was a בכור, bechor, if we're only finding out
it was a בכור bechor, from the כהן kohen himself, so most
of the time who knows what the other status of the other
person's sheep is in a flock is? So you understand this opens
up this wide, you know, area now so most of the time
I don't know who what animals of yours are a בכור. bechor,
So now you are believed in a wide range of cases assuming
that that is believed. So let's take a look. ובא אחד ואמר
שהוא בכור ומומו עמו, U-va echad v'amar she-hu bechor u-mumo imo, נאמן,
it's believed. So right, Michael says, of course. מאי קמשמע לן? Mai
ka mashma lan? What's it telling you? שהפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר,
shehapes asar hu hapes hitir, that the same mouth that forbids is
the mouth that permits, meaning of course you should be believed, since
without you saying anything I would have assumed it wasn't a בכור.
bechor, How would I have known? So it's if I'm going to
believe you that it is a בכור, bechor I should believe you
that it got its blemish on its own. So that's not a
חידוש once I'm believing you, once I only know it's a בכור
bechor, because of your own testimony. So the גמרא Gemara says that's
obviously. תנינא, tanina, we taught it in a משנה, mishnah, האשה שאמרה
אשת איש הייתי וגרושה אני, ha-ishah she-amrah eshet ish hayiti u-gerushah ani,
that's a woman comes and we had no idea what her personal
history was and she says, yeah I used to be married but
now I'm divorced. נאמנת, ne'emenet, she's believed, שהפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר,
shehapes asar hu hapes hitir, the same mouth that made her forbidden
when she claimed she was married makes her permissible when she claims
she's divorced. So you see that if we believe you partway, we
believe you the whole way if we didn't know evidence beforehand. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. מהו דתימא אימא עד התא התם הוא
דאי בעי לא אמרה, mahu de-teima eima ad hata hatham hu de-ba'ei
lo amrah, there she could have just not said anything and we
would have assumed she's single because we had no knowledge otherwise. אבל
הכא, aval hacha, here, the כהן kohen did not have a choice
to admit that it was a בכור. bechor. Why didn't he have
a choice? אבל הכא דלא סגי דלא אמרה, aval hacha de-lo sagi
de-lo amrah, he had no choice but to admit that it was
a בכור. bechor Why is that? דקדשים בחוץ לא אכיל, de-kadshim bachutz
lo achil, he himself would not want to eat a בכור bechor,
outside the בית המקדש, meaning that while it is true we suspect
them of inflicting the blemish on their own, the owner or כהנים
as a class, but we don't think everyone compartmentalizes, everyone rationalizes. So
okay, it's a one of they I'll make the blemish on my
own, but I'm not going to eat a קרבן without a blemish
outside the בית המקדש, that's a חיוב כרת, chiyuv karet, that's a
big, big sin. So therefore, let's get into the psychology of this
guy. He's got a בכור, bechor. it's got a מום, he's got
to bring it into town and show the מום to a חכם
chacham so the חכם chacham can tell us that this is a
genuine blemish. And he is not going to lie about that. He
will not eat this בכור bechor if it does not have a
real blemish. So therefore, don't tell me, oh, well look, since I'm
believing him that it since since he admitted it was a בכור
bechor I should believe how it got the blemish. No, he has
to come to town and ask a חכם chacham to look at
it because he wouldn't allow himself to eat it without it being
a valid blemish. So therefore, maybe since he had no other choice,
I shouldn't believe him that it got the blemish on its own.
So let's take a look.
So it wasn't a בכור.
bechor
Oh, but he had no choice, he had to show it to
a חכם chacham to get a ruling on the blemish, right? And
since he had a he would not have eaten it without it
being a legitimate blemish and he had to show it to a
חכם. chacham. What's he going to do? I'm just curious, were this
a בכור, bechor. would this be a good blemish? Okay, no, he
couldn't have said that.
He had to show
it and say it was a בכור. bechor?
Yes, so therefore since he had to admit it was a בכור,
why should we believe him about how it got its blemish? The
only reason we believe him is we said nothing was compelling him
to admit it was a בכור, but now we see otherwise. So
there actually is a
big about how he got his blemish or that it how,
how, that's the entire question here is how. The חכם chacham decides
whether it is a blemish. The only question is whether it got
it on its own or not. אימא
לא הפה שאסר הוא, eima lo hapes asar hu, it's not the
same mouth that made it forbidden, meaning he didn't do that freely,
he had to admit it. קא משמע לן that he is believed.
Now you make such a good case, so why is he believed?
Since he has to. So let's just wait, so why is he
believed? דאי משום האי, de-ei mishum hai, if that were the reason,
הוי משני במום דניכר. havei meshanei be-mumo de-nikkar. Okay, thank you Michael,
I know you anticipate the גמרא, Gemara. but let's let everybody else
stay with the flow for a while. Okay, so anyway, so no,
because if he really is doing it himself, he wouldn't have made
a blemish that needed a ruling of the חכם. chacham. He would
have made a much more obvious blemish that didn't need a ruling
and he would have stayed in his farm and not bothered bringing
it to a חכם. chacham. Why get in trouble? Make a big
obvious blemish, you know it's okay, you shecht it, you eat it,
if you really are just trying to avoid קדשים בחוץ. kadshim bachutz.
So since it had the suspect blemish, why do you have to
give himself so much צרות tzaros if he was really making this
up? It must be that he's honest, that it got it by
itself, because otherwise he would have just avoided the whole problem and
that's why we believe him. Okay, so now, by the way, now
you realize that if that's true and if unless we knew independently
that it was a בכור, we believe somebody, then that makes the
whole scenario so much easier. Imagine, see how the גמרא Gemara. has
completely narrowed this issue about not believing anybody. First of all it
says the only person we don't believe is the person himself, we
even believe family members, okay, maybe the person and his spouse. And
then it actually says and as long as we didn't know beforehand
that it was a בכור, we believe we also even believe him.
Okay, so it's very, very much narrows the scope of that. The
only question I have is, is that let's say the person actually
we do believe him but let's say actually I don't know that
it got it on its own, I just know that I didn't
or nobody I know of, you know I know I didn't I
know I didn't inflict the blemish. I don't know as a positive
fact that it got it by itself. Presumably, you know, once it's
not a question about you needing to believe me, it's about just,
you know, I don't know, I don't know the answer to that.
I could imagine that once it's a case where you believe me
anyway, that that's sufficient, but that's not clear to me. Do we
need positive testimony that it got that you witnessed it getting it
by itself or once we believe the owner like in a case
where we didn't know it's a בכור, we'll also just accept the
statement that he didn't do it and nobody else he knows did
it.
Very basically an interesting question of personal values and character as to
you
know where you go with some of this stuff.
Right. Absolutely.
There are certain people who if they think it could have been
done by someone, you know, they won't take advantage of it whereas
somebody else looks at it and they're like okay.
Exactly. I mean that's why this גמרא Gemara is so fascinating because
it really deals with questions and it's not hesitant to suspect the
כהנים on the one hand, but on the other hand it then
goes ahead and tries to really sort of I think nail this,
you know, so you sort of see those those dynamics playing out.
So let's take a look. The גמרא says like this: מתקיף לה
מר בר רב אשי, Maskif lei Mar bar Rav Ashi, so מר
בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi asks this: מאי שנא, Mai
shna, so the fact that you're going to believe כהנים because he
said that he could have shut up, he didn't have to say
anything, I'll show you that sometimes even if somebody could have shut
up, we still don't believe him. How's it different from the following
case? ההוא גברא דאוגר ליה חמרא לחבריה, Hahu gavra de-ogir lei chamra
le-chavrei, somebody rented a donkey to his friend. ואמר ליה לא תיזיל
באורחא דנהר פקוד, Ve-amar lei lo teizil be-orcha de-Nahar Pekod, don't go
by the way of the river פקוד Pekod or the Wadi פקוד
Pekod דאיכא מיא, de-ika maya, there's water there and the חמרא chamra
will slip and die and whatever. זיל באורחא דנש, Zil be-orcha de-Nash,
go by the way of נש Nash דליכא מיא, de-leika maya, there's
no water. אזל באורחא דנהר פקוד, Azal be-orcha de-Nahar Pekod, of course
he completely ignored the guy and he went by the way of
נהר פקוד, Nahar Pekod, ומת חמרא, u-mit chamra, and the donkey died.
ואתא ואמר ליה, Ve-ata ve-amar lei, and he came back and he
said: באורחא דנהר פקוד אזלי, Be-orcha de-Nahar Pekod azli, it's true I
went I didn't follow your advice I went by the Wadi of
פקוד, Pekod, ומיהו מיא לא הוו, u-mihu maya lo havu, but you
know what, it happened to be a dry Wadi and there was
no water. Now why is that relevant? Because if there actually was
water, then he was negligent. And no matter what happened to it,
he has to pay right? Because he's a שוכר socher and you
pay for negligence and other types of damages unless it's a complete
אונס. ones. But if there was no water, then even though he
disobeyed the instructions, since there was no water and there wasn't negligence,
then the death was accidental, he would be exempt. So do you
believe him that there was no water or not? ואמר רבא, Ve-amar
Rava, and רבא said, מה לי לשקר, mah lei leshaker, why what
why does he need to lie? אי בעי אמר באורחא דנש אזלי,
Iy ba'ei amar be-orcha de-Nash azli, he could have just said that
I went the other way. So therefore because he could have shut
up, we believe him that there was no water there. ואמר אביי,
Ve-amar Abaye, but אביי Abaye says, מה לי לשקר במקום עדים לא
אמרינן. mah lei leshaker be-makom eidim lo amrinan. We
don't say, oh he didn't have to lie if it contradicts witnesses.
Now what witnesses are there? So there are no witnesses but some
things are seen as so patently obvious that it's as if there
were witnesses. That there was water in נהר פקוד, Nahar Pekod, for
some reason אביי Abaye is considering that that's considered like of course
there's going to be water there. You know it's like your kid
tells you this whole fabricated story where you know that that's like
a blatant lie. So even though, you know, you could have said
something else and you could have shut up and even though you
had no reason to lie, if in there is something that to
us is patently obvious false, then we're
going to then we're not going to believe you, okay? That's מה
לי לשקר במקום עדים. mah lei leshaker be-makom eidim. So the גמרא
assumes here, since you've just gotten through telling me that you suspect
כהנים and that you suspect the owner, so even if he had
no reason to lie, why don't we still say but to us
it's still obvious that you're lying? But there's an obvious difference there
which the גמרא is going to spell out. Let's take a look.
So the גמרא says like this: הכי השתא, Hachi hashta, what type
of comparison is that? התם ודאי איכא
מיא, Hatam vadai ika maya, when it comes to that Wadi we
can say there was definitely water. And even though you didn't have
to tell your whole story, once you told it we don't believe
you, okay, because it's patently false.
הכא ודאי
שדי
ביה
מומא? Hacha vadai shadei bei muma? I'm sorry I misread that word.
הכא ודאי שדי ביה
מומא? Hacha vadai shadei bei muma? Do we think that every כהן
kohen definitely puts a blemish in their own sheep? No. חששא הוא,
Chashasha hu, it's a suspicion. ובמקום חששא אמרינן מה לי לשקר. U-ve-makom
chashasha amrinan mah lei leshaker. To counteract the suspicion we say you
didn't have to lie. Meaning what do we say? We don't say
oh it's patently obvious that every single כהן kohen, always puts a
מום in every single one of their sheep. חס ושלום, Chas ve-shalom,
we never say that. We say sometimes some כהנים will do it.
So you come and you tell me this was a בכור, you
didn't have to tell me that and you tell me it was
a בכור and you tell me it got the מום by itself,
I'm going to believe you. I'll assume you're of those כהנים that's
honest that doesn't do it by yourself, it's not going against something
that's patently false. Okay.
But if you're חשוד on that though then they wouldn't believe you
in that other case.
Not necessarily, because it's still not מקום עדים. makom eidim. מקום עדים
makom eidim means that it's true if you didn't have to tell
me anything but once you told it to me you said something
patently false, we won't accept it. But even if somebody is personally
I don't know I would assume that even if somebody is personally
suspect, it doesn't mean that they do it a hundred percent of
the time, okay? So what to get to a stage where we
consider it to be obviously and patently false, that we're not saying.
Because so you'd be very suspect then if we knew this
was a בכור, we wouldn't believe you that it
got its מום on its own. Right, which is basically the rule,
we don't believe כהנים when or the owners when we know how
it when we know that it was a בכור. If we didn't
know it's a בכור and you didn't have to tell me it
was a בכור, then we're going to believe you because we're not
going to say that you always
Yes.
And we started to mention yesterday briefly about this possibility of making
a מום before the
animal is born. Yes.
That's—well you can't really say that, it's an interesting question because you
can't say that by the כהן kohen because the כהן kohen didn't
have the animal when it was born, the ישראל Yisrael did. But
I suppose it's an interesting question about believing a כהן kohen. about
his own בכורות bechorot since it was his own בכור. I don't
know if you have to, but if it's a בכור that was
born to his own flock, not that he got from ישראל, Yisrael,
then maybe we should believe him because if he wanted to trick
he could have made a blemish before it even came out of
its mother.
It's an interesting question. Yeah.
If if that was accepted, then why didn't everybody just do that
to begin with and solve the problem?
Because the ישראל Yisrael has no incentive to do it. It's my
sheep, I'm not the one that's going to benefit from this. I'm
giving it to you, you're the כהן. Kohen Why should I go
to the effort of doing that in my בכור to be nice
to you? You know, okay, it'll be nice if I did that
to be nice to you, but I'm not necessarily—but there's not that
much of an incentive. But but there's the other question you're asking
is an interesting one. Why not believe כהנים about their own animals
because they could have solved the problem themselves. So let's take a
look at how the גמרא continues. Okay, so the גמרא says, okay,
יתיב רב עינא וקאמר להא שמעתא בלא גברא. Yativ Rav Ina veka'amar
leha shema'ata belo gavra. רב עינא Rav Ina was telling over this
whole discussion without telling who was attributed to, this discussion about we
didn't know it was a בכור beforehand without attributing it to
רבי אלעאי. Rabbi Ilai. אמר ליה רב זוטא לרב עינא, Amar lei
Rav Zuta leRav Ina, אנן משמיה דרבי אלעאי מתנינן לה. Anan mishmeih
deRabbi Ilai matninan lah. Actually we taught that over in the name
of רבי אלעאי, Rabbi Ilai, which was how the גמרא originally presented
it. Fine. Okay. That's a slightly different variation of how it was
originally told over. רבי צדוק הוה ליה בוכרא. Rabbi Tzadok hava lei
buchra. רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok had a בכור. רמא ליה שערי בסלא.
Rama lei sha'arei besala. He threw some some what do you call
barley in a basket for it to eat of נצרי nasrei which
was קלעי דחרובא וארבי דקלוף. kala'ei decharuva ve'arvei dekaluf. There's a question
here exactly of the גרסא girsa but basically what it means was
it was a basket made out of like types of reeds or
you know a wicker basket which obviously has sharp edges. And he
put the barley in this wicker basket for the animal to eat.
ובהדי דקאכיל, Uvahadei deka'achil, as the animal was chewing the barley, איבזע
ספותיה, ivza sefoteih, its lip got cut on the edge of some
of the wicker of the basket. אתא לקמיה דרבי יהושע. Ata lekameih
deRabbi Yehoshua. So he came to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So now
this רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok was a כהן. Kohen Okay, this happened
to his animal, it happened by accident, he didn't intend it.
He came to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. אמר ליה, Amar lei, כלום
חילקנו בין חבר לעם הארץ? Kelum chilaknu bein chaver le'am ha'aretz? When
the question about not trusting כהנים is there a difference between a
כהן who's a who's a חבר, chaver, remember the חבר, chaver, the
friend, right, the כהן that is a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham or
that's part of this community of purity which basically means people that
we trust as opposed to כהנים that are just part of the
you know general people of the land, not part of this special
group of people that we trust or of תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim.
So maybe a normal כהן off the street we don't trust, but
maybe a כהן who's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham who's one of
us quote unquote maybe we do trust. So I'm a כהן, I'm
telling you what happened, are you prepared to trust me? אמר ליה
Amar lei, רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, הין, hein, yes we do make
that distinction, you are trusted, we're not going to suspect you.
אתא לקמיה דרבן גמליאל. Ata lekameih deRabban Gamliel. Then he came to
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and asked him the same question. Now that's
first of all that's good here's advice for you: once you get
the answer that you want, stop talking, stop asking. אמר ליה, Amar
lei it's actually true they tell us other things as well you
know, it's like it's like you know just stop talking once once
you got the response you're looking for. אמר ליה, Amar lei, חילקנו
בין חבר לעם הארץ? Chilaknu bein chaver le'am ha'aretz? Do we make
a distinction? אמר ליה Amar lei רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, לאו, lav,
no we don't make a distinction. וואו. Wow. אמר ליה, Amar lei
so he said back to him, והרי רבי יהושע אמר לי הין?
Veharei Rabbi Yehoshua amar li hein? But רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua told
me we do make a distinction between whether it's a כהן who's
a חבר chaver or an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. אמר לו, Amar
lo, המתן עד שיעלו בעלי תריסין. Hamten ad sheya'alu ba'alei terisin. He
says wait till the people of the shield come in, meaning wait
till the students of the בית המדרש beit hamidrash enter in. There's
a whole you know
military metaphor here of the like fighting the fight of תורה. So
the בית המדרש. beit hamidrash. Wait till they come into the בית
המדרש. beit hamidrash. תריס Tris is I think a shield, like a
like an army shield, like you know like so it's funny also
you didn't say swords, you said shield which is more defensive than
something. Anyway but let's wait till the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim come
in and we can discuss this in a more public forum.
I'm mostly in here with you.
Yeah you need I know that's what I think that he is
going to put רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua on the defensive, exactly. כיוון
שנכנסו לבית המדרש, Keivan shenichnasu leveit hamidrash, everybody came into the study
hall. עמד השואל ושאל. Amad hasho'el vesha'al. So the questioner stood up
and asked. כלום חילקנו בין חבר לעם הארץ? Kelum chilaknu bein chaver
le'am ha'aretz? Do we make a distinction between a חבר chaver and
an עם הארץ am ha'aretz when it comes to trusting the owner
or the כהנים for בכור? אמר ליה רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, לאו,
lav, no. So he had said before yes, now he's saying no,
because רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua sort of knew what was up, knew
that he was going to be challenged and knew the answer probably
that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel wanted to hear. So that's what he
said. אמר ליה רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, והלא משמך אמרו לי הין?
Vehala mishmecha amru li hein? But
I I had a report, here's an ADH, I had a report
that you said yes. יהושע עמוד על רגליך ויעידו בך. Yehoshua amod
al raglecha veya'idu bach.
So now... he really had to strip down יהושע, Yehoshua, he said,
arise on your feet and let people and let them testify against
you that you actually had ruled otherwise than my ruling. עמד רבי
יהושע על רגליו. Amad Rabbi Yehoshua Al Raglav. So רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua stood up on his feet. ואמר Ve'amar and he said, היך
אעשה? Heich E'eseh? Now what can I do? אם לחי אני והוא
מת, Im Lechai Ani Vehu Meis, had I been alive and he
were dead—that's interesting—יכול החי להכחיש את המת, Yachol Hachai Lehach'chish Es Hameis,
then I could maybe have gotten away with my my sort of
my claim that I had never said it, then nobody would have
been around to contradict me. אבל עכשיו שאני חי והוא חי, Aval
Achshav She'ani Chai Vehu Chai, I'm alive and he's alive, היך יכול
החי להכחיש את החי? Heich Yachol Hachai Lehach'chish Es Hachai? How can
I contradict him? I'm trying to get out of this. I knew
I was going to get into trouble if I contradicted him, so
I tried to sort of cover it up by saying that I
had said otherwise. I said no. But now he's got me. He's
got me to my rights. He's got evidence otherwise and I have
no way of getting out of it. I can't, so I can't
claim that I never said it. והיה רבן גמליאל יושב ודורש. Vehayah
Rabban Gamliel Yoseiv Vedoreish. So it was like sending the kid to
the corner to wear the dunce hat. So he had רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua standing up and sort of in this embarrassed position and
then they went on with the שיעור. shiur. He spent the rest
of the time רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel going ahead and lecturing and
learning, teaching תורה. ורבי יהושע עומד על רגליו, Verabbi Yehoshua Omeid Al
Raglav, and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua standing there being singled out. עד
שרננו כל העם, Ad Sherineinu Kol Ha'am, until everybody started murmuring and
felt that this was completely disrespectful of רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. ואמרו
לחוצפית המתורגמן עמוד. Ve'amru Lechutzpis Hameturgaman Amode. They said to חוצפית Chutzpis
who was the one who actually was the projector of רבן גמליאל—like
Rabban Gamliel רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would sort of say his דרשה
drasha and then חוצפית Chutzpis המתורגמן, Hameturgaman, who as תוספות points out
was one of the עשרה הרוגי מלכות, Asarah Harugei Malchus, would either
translate it or would project it more loudly. So he was the
one that was allowed רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel to do his teaching.
He was the reciter. And they said to—the people were so offended
at the by the way רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was being treated,
they said to him עמוד, stop. It's like turned off the mic,
is essentially what they did. They didn't like what רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel was doing, they turned off the mic. ועמד, Ve'amad, and he
stopped, he stopped sort of in his role. And then רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel was not allowed to continue teaching because they had to
put an end to this. Now, this is a very fascinating story.
It is half of the story. In ברכות Berachos you have the
whole story. In ברכות Berachos you have a very similar discussion about
whether תפילת ערבית Tefillas Arvis was רשות reshus or חובה, chovah, was
it obligatory or permissible. And the same thing happened. רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua said one thing, but then somebody reported it to רבן גמליאל,
Rabban Gamliel, it was the opposite of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. He
said, wait till the בעלי תריסין ba'alei terisin come to the בית
המדרש. Beis Hamedrash. The exact same scenario. Stand up, testify against you.
And then it said they silenced him. And then it's actually quite
interesting because it actually—that גמרא actually refers explicitly to our גמרא. And
it says, how long are we going to take this treatment—this is
what the people said—from רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel? It said last year
he treated, he dressed down רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in the ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah story. You remember there's a whole ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah story where there's a question about what day was ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and so on. It says, and then there was the
time that he mistreated רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in בכורות, Bechoros, in
the רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok story. And it explicitly
says המעשה דבכורות ברבי צדוק. Hama'aseh Debechoros Berabbi Tzadok. Like, it directly
refers to our גמרא. So anyway, it says so they basically—there was
a whole little coup where they tried to dethrone רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel because they thought that he was lording over his authority. And
actually it reflects the reality that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael there
was a joining of political and rabbinical authority. Right? The הלל, Hillel,
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel,
that whole line were both the נשיא Nasi and the head of
the בית המדרש. Beis Hamedrash. And there was a joining of those
two authorities. It's interesting and thinking about חנוכה Chanukah that's coming up—about
the joining of political and religious authority. And they thought that he
was sort of, for he was, right, he was so focused on
asserting his authority that it was mistreating of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
and completely wrong. But anyway, so there's a whole story there about
that whole little palace coup and how the whole thing sort of
in the end got resolved. One minute. But the point that I
would like to make here as perhaps a possible subtext of this
story, not necessarily the other ones, is I also think what's fascinating
here is why—why is it such an issue? Do we make a
distinction between this type of כהן or that? Now, could be it's
not a big issue. He just didn't want anybody contradicting him, like
the same way why is it such a big issue whether תפילת
ערבית Tefillas Arvis is רשות reshus or חובה. chovah. I mean, okay,
it's a halachic debate and maybe רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was just
so assertive or defensive about his own positions and authority.
But—and this might just be my own little דרוש—I drush wonder if
something else is going on here as well, which
is: as was pointed out, if you start suspecting the כהנים post-בית
המקדש, it's part of a general also trend as the גמרא sort
of alluded to before, of כהנים losing their status as the religious
authorities. And who takes—after the בית המקדש the rabbis take their place.
And now concomitant with that, you have not only have they formally
lost their role, but they're also suspect, right, as opposed to the
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and the חברים chaverim and whatever. חברים chaverim
become תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and they become the ones that can
be trusted. So then the very fact—maybe there was also an aspect
here
that it's important that we don't trust any כהן. Meaning if you
trust the כהנים *Kohanim* that are the תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim*, it
could be because of their status as תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim*, but
also is a way of giving maybe indirect, giving some recognition
to the status of כהן *Kohen*. It's not really because we're only
trusting them because they're תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim*, but in terms of
thinking about the power issue going on here, you could see how
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* might have had a vested interest in saying
we should not be believing כהנים *Kohanim* across the board. It's a
very clear way of making it clear that they do not have,
they are not the sort of religious authorities, and he, who was
both the combination of religious and political authority, he was the authority.
Yes.
Do we have in the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, do we have any laws
against publicly humiliating another individual?
Yes, there are the... shaming is... right, right. And obviously the people
did react.
I mean, I think everybody reacted because it was a natural thing
to do. But beyond that, it seems to me there's a law...
Yeah, I mean, there are things like הלבנת פנים *halbanat panim* and
all of those questions. I mean, look, it raises more general issues
about some of these בין אדם לחברו *bein adam l'chavero*, right, how
people act in ישיבה *yeshiva*. But I mean, for example, I'll give
you another... I'll answer your question with another question, which is,
right, what Seth said to me, and I really agree with him,
that it's so serious that it should be raised here. And Seth,
my quoting Seth, he said, this is the culture of the ישיבה
*yeshiva*. Right. And I hear this from young kids. I hear about
teachers
humiliating a child in class, and I find that to be abominable.
I can't even...
It is, it is. And I look, I want to point out,
right, heightening the question without giving an answer here, that in some
of these בין אדם לחברו *bein adam l'chavero* הלכות *halachot*, there's also
questions about when might they be allowed because they're seen to be,
I'm not saying that's the case, but they're, but they might be
sort of seen to be as for the person's better good, like
hitting somebody to for a parent or teacher, which happened all the
time in the past, right, hitting somebody because they felt that that
was
educationally important.
Or the גמרא *Gemara* says obviously an explicit prohibition in the תורה
*Torah* is taking vengeance, נקמה *nekama*. But the גמרא *Gemara* says that
any תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* that is not נוטר ונוקם כנחש *noter
v'nokem k'nachash*, does not be sort of bear a grudge and take
vengeance like a snake, is not really defending the honor of תורה
*Torah*. So there are, so
I'm heightening the problem, but I'm saying there are interesting questions about
how you figure out the parameters of some of these בין אדם
לחברו *bein adam l'chavero* הלכות *halachot*, if they're seen to be sort
of other justifying sort of context. What does that do to those
prohibitions? So, and then the question is, it's one thing to say
what it does in sort of principle, but then is what if
in practice it
actually is
really terrible and is devastating and is counterproductive? So those are all
excellent points. So I'm just highlighting that question. Okay, let's continue a
little bit. Yes.
Also an alternative interpretation of רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*. Yes.
You know, he says, how can I, how can I deny somebody
else, another person is contradicting me? Well, you could deny it. He
says, she says.
Right, right. And, but that's answered by, he says, יהושע עמוד על
רגליך ויעידו בך *Yehoshua amod al raglecha v'ya'idu bach*. Right. Let them...
The person who asked the question is testifying for him. Oh, I
see. Interesting.
So possibly it was in public. But in that case...
תוספות *Tosafot* thinks that... yeah, go ahead.
I think there's a subtext
that the "he" he says I can't contradict is רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel* and not רבי צדוק *Rabbi Tzadok*.
I would agree with that. I would agree that... if he
were already dead, then I wouldn't have to deal with all of
these, all of these political tug-of-wars, right? I totally agree with that.
In terms of ויעידו בך *v'ya'idu bach*, תוספות *Tosafot* thinks that that's
a borrowed phrase because from a different story. But, but yeah, I
think you're right, meaning I do think that the subtext is that
he wishes he, רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* wasn't around so he didn't
have to deal with all of those issues. All right, let's try,
we have five minutes left, to get at least a little bit
further. נאמן הכהן לומר הראיתי בכור זה ובעל מום הוא *Ne'eman hakohen
lomar her'eiti bechor zeh u'ba'al mum hu*. So a כהן *Kohen* is
believed, although a כהן *Kohen* is not believed to say how the
blemish came, although remember we've radically limited that now. We said it's
only limited to the owner himself and his wife, and that we've
also said that what do you call it, that it's believed if
we didn't know beforehand that it was a בכור *bechor*. But now
we're saying that a כהן *Kohen* is believed to say, so first
of all we've radically limited how it got a מום *mum*, but
he is believed to say that this מום *mum*, let's say we
know how it got a מום *mum*, other people testified it happened
by itself, and now he's telling me, oh, this sage פסק *paskened*
to me that it was a genuine מום *mum*. That he is
believed about, even though he's not believed how it got a מום
*mum*. Let's see why there's a difference. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב
*Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, נאמן הכהן לומר בכור זה נתן לי
ישראל במומו *Ne'eman hakohen lomar bechor zeh natan li Yisrael b'mumo*. He's
also believed to say, I got this בכור *bechor* from a... ישראל
*Yisrael* with the blemish already there, and I didn't make the blemish.
So why is that different than just saying how it got the
blemish? So let's take a look and try to understand these cases
he's believed. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama* why's that? כל מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי
לא משקרי בה אינשי *Kol milta d'avida l'igluyei lo meshakrei bei inshi*.
Here's an important principle. Anything that will be uncovered people don't lie
about. So since, since all I would have to do is if
you say you got it from this ישראל *Yisrael* with the מום
*mum*, I could just turn and ask the ישראל *Yisrael* whether that's
true or not. So therefore you're not going to lie. That's his
explanation of why you're believed in that case. So אמר רב אשי
אף אנן נמי תנינא *Amar Rav Ashi af anan nami tanina*, that's
also פשט *pshat* in our משנה *mishna*. נאמן הכהן לומר הראיתי בכור
זה על מום לחכם ובעל מום הוא *Ne'eman hakohen lomar hereti bechor
zeh al mum l'chacham u'ba'al mum hu*. I showed this בכור *bechor*
to a sage and he told me that it was a genuine
blemish. Why don't we assume he's lying that it's not a blemish?
Presumably because I could always just ask the sage and find out
if that's true. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama* what's the reason? לאו משום
דאמרינן כל מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי לא משקרי בה אינשי *Lav mishum d'amrinan
kol milta d'avida l'igluyei lo meshakrei bei inshi*? Isn't it because we
say anything that will be revealed people don't lie about? You can
always just ask the sage. No, that's not the reason. התם הוא
דקדשים בחוץ לא אכיל *Hatam hu d'kodshim bachutz lo achil*. There, as
we said before, the only thing a כהן *kohen* is suspect about
is about making the blemish. He is not going to treat something
that's not a blemish as a blemish. He does not want to
eat a קרבן *korban* outside the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. So he's
not going to lie about whether it's a blemish. He might lie
about how it got to be there, but he won't lie about
whether it's a blemish. There, he doesn't want to eat קדשים בחוץ
*kodshim bachutz*. So here, he's certainly not going to lie about whether
it's a blemish. אבל הכא *Aval hacha* here where it's a question
of how it got it, כיון דחשידי *keivan d'chashidi* if you're suspect
for making the blemish, חשידי *chashidi* you'll say that you got it
from the ישראל *Yisrael* as well. And we, the fact that we
can check up on your story does not necessarily mean you're telling
the truth. And you know by the way, we know this all
the time, right? People will interview for a job, they'll put down
where they went to school, they'll put down references, and you know,
much, much more than you would think, nobody bothers checking up the
references and they get away with it. You take a risk, nothing
ventured, nothing lost. So it's not necessarily true that just because you
can check up my story I won't lie. Okay, so מתיב רב
שיזבי *mativ Rav Shizbi*, so רב שיזבי *Rav Shizbi* asks, האומר למי
שאינו נאמן על המעשר קח לי ממי שהוא נאמן או ממי שמעשר
*ha'omer l'mi she'eino ne'eman al hama'aser kach li miman shehu ne'eman o
miman shehu me'aser*. If you tell somebody, I go and I tell
somebody who normally is not careful about taking מעשר *ma'aser*, and I
ask them to go buy food for me, and I say, buy
food but I only want you to buy it from a person
that can be trusted to take מעשר *ma'aser*, or from a person
that's a middleman but he buys from people and he takes his
own מעשר *ma'aser*. So you, the שליח *shaliach*, normally do not care
about this, but I'm asking you for my sake, buy it only
from a person that normally is careful.
Okay, אינו נאמן *eino ne'eman*, you're not believed to say you did
it because for you it doesn't matter. You'll just do what's easiest.
Okay, even though I told you to do it from a person,
you'll just do from the cheapest easiest person. אמאי *Ammai*, why is
that true? נימא כל מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי לא משקרי בה אינשי *Neima
kol milta d'avida l'igluyei lo meshakrei bei inshi*? You tell me you
bought it from so-and-so, I could check up, oh you bought it
from a trustworthy guy, I could check up your story. So why
don't we assume that you actually did it? I can check up
on it. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, no, שאני התם *shani hatam*,
there it's different, דאית ליה לאשתמוטי *d'it lei l'ishtamutei*. You could always
say, oh, you didn't consider Frank trustworthy? I thought he was trustworthy.
So you can always tell me that, you know, the guy you
bought it from you assumed he was trustworthy. And that's why I
don't believe you. You won't really get caught in the lie. Okay,
interesting right now having discussion about being caught in a lie right
juxtaposed to the previous story with רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*.
Anyway, סיפא ודאי מסייע ליה *seifa vadai mesayei lei*, but the end
of that ברייתא *braita* about מעשר *ma'aser* does support you. It says
if you say מאיש פלוני *mi'ish ploni*, you say oh yeah, I
went ahead and I bought it from this particular person. You don't
just say I bought it from a trustworthy guy. You say I
bought it from that guy, that you know, Dov
Linz.
Right. No, I'm sorry, not that's what you say, excuse me, not
just what the שליח *shaliach* says. When I tell you go buy,
if you tell me you got it from that guy, then I'll
go and talk to the guy and say how could you buy
it, he wasn't trustworthy, you'll say oh I thought he was trustworthy.
But if I tell you I only want you to buy from
that store over there that has that השגחה *hashgacha*, okay, and I
tell you specifically which store, which person I want you to buy
it from, then
הרי זה נאמן *harei zeh ne'eman*, you are believed. Why? Because I
can always find out if you bought it from, I'll go to
that store and ask if you bought it there. So it's, so
the גמרא *Gemara* says no, that's a special case. התם כיון דאית
ליה תביעה *Hatam keivan d'it lei tveiya*, since I am demanding and
being very specific, מרתת *mirtat*, you are very afraid. You see if
he's, if Dov is willing to be so specific, he's going to
check up on me. Okay, so that doesn't explain the average case
where I'm not coming and making demands, you're just offering the information.
Are we there assume that because I could check, that that's going
to keep you honest? Okay, but if you clear that I'm concerned,
obviously you're going to be honest. Okay, so we will end with
that here with that question about whether the fact that you can
check up on somebody's story necessarily is what keeps them honest. פשט
*pshat* in our משנה *mishna* is that the כהן *kohen* is believed
that the מום *mum* is a genuine מום *mum* because he's not
believed to lie about, to lie that it is a מום *mum*.
He's only, he's I mean he's not suspect to lie that it
is a מום *mum*, he's only suspect to lie how it became
to be a מום *mum*. And now the question is, is that...
If he gives me a story that can be checked up, well
then I'll be prepared to believe him because then it is עבידא
לגלויי. avida legiluya. So we'll continue tomorrow.
If that's the case with the
כהן then how do we believe any כהן at all? How do
we believe him on
any מום that he presents?
He's definitely not suspect
to lie that
it's a מום. What if it was really a מום עובר mum
over and it's something that is going to pass and he says
it's a permanent מום? Why do we believe him on that? That's
not עבידא לגלויי.